We are resume here after we'll be doing ל"ו Lamed Vav from
the top but we resume four lines from the bottom ל"א ע"א.
Lamed Aleph Amud Aleph. אמר רב המנונא, Amar Rav Hamnuna, so we
are dealing with models of תפילה tefillah particularly the question about issues
of כוונה. kavana. We had a very important גמרא gemara minute ago
about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the difference between how he would
שוקל shokel and the immense כוונה kavana he would have when he
was private and how he would not do it בציבור be-tzibur and
partly that's an issue about concern for others but partly it's an
issue about balancing the two modes of תפילה בציבור tefillah be-tzibur which
is the communal experience and maybe more כנגד קרבנות k'neged korbanot and
the individual prayer which is much more with a focus on the
כוונה kavana and now we're going to hone in on that particularly
about חנה Hannah and the model of חנה. Hannah. So let's take
a look.
אמר רב המנונא, Amar Rav Hamnuna, כמה הלכתא
גברוותא איכא למשמע מהני קראי דחנה. Kama hilchata givarvata ika le-mishma me-hanei
karai de-Hannah. How many you know huge הלכות halachot powerful הלכה halacha
can you infer from the verses of חנה. Hannah. וחנה היא מדברת
על לבה, Ve-Hannah hi medaberet al libah, Hannah was speaking to her
heart. מכאן למתפלל צריך שיכוון לבו. Mikan le-mitpallel tzarich she-yekhaven libo.
So it's speaking not just on her heart, but you know from
her heart. So the prayer is not just saying the words, it's
about actually having כוונה kavana and feeling and being in touch with
what you are saying. רק שפתיה נעות, Rak sefateha na'ot,
only her lips were moving. מכאן למתפלל שיחתוך בשפתיו. Mikan le-mitpallel she-yachtoch
bi-sfatav.
It's not just about thinking the words, it's actually about articulating, literally
cutting with your lips, moving your lips. But it's not articulating to
the point of being audible. וקולה לא ישמע, Ve-kolah lo yishama, her
voice could not be heard. מכאן שאסור להגביה קולו בתפלתו. Mikan she-asur
le-hagbi'ah kolo bi-tfilato. You cannot lift up your voice in תפילה. tefillah.
So it's sort of the silent prayer but it's still with a
moving of the lips which is a fascinating, you know, sort of
balance, right? Because normally הלכה halacha is that if you speak it
should be audible, you know. I you know sometimes we have by
the שמע Shema we had a whole discussion about what happens if
you can't hear your own שמע. Shema. If you are unable to
be audible, you know, and here it's totally about the movement of
the lips and
without it actually being audible. There actually are some אחרונים achronim that
wonder whether if it's enough since תפילה tefillah is fundamentally עבודה שבלב,
avodah she-ba-lev, is it enough to just think the words of תפילה?
tefillah? Generally the assumption is not, but there is a צד tzad
that has that whole question that it's actually some type of a
speech but almost like a silent speech. So ויחשבה עלי
לשכורה, Vayachsheveha Eli le-shikora, Eli thought that she was drunk. מכאן Mikan
and that obviously was a problem. So מכאן ששכור אסור
להתפלל, Mikan she-shikor asur le-hitpallel, that somebody who's drunk cannot pray. Right?
Even if maybe you could have minimal כוונה kavana to be יוצא,
yotzei, but it's an idea of standing before God and therefore that
is forbidden. ויאמר אליה עלי, Vayomer eleiha Eli, and Eli said to
her, עד מתי
תשתכרין, Ad matai tistakarin, until how long will you be drunk? Right?
Get rid of your wine. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Eleazar, מכאן
לרואה בחברו דבר מגונה, mikan le-ro'eh be-chavero davar meguneh, from here you
see that if somebody sees דבר שאינו הגון, davar she-eino hagun, somebody
sees in his friend something that is inappropriate, as תוספות Tosafot points
out, even if it's not technically a חטא chet or a violation,
I mean, but nevertheless if it's inappropriate behavior, צריך להוכיחו, tzarich le-hochiho,
if you care about that person you will give them some type
of a מוסר. mussar. You'll give them some type of a, you
know, of a remonstration. So Eli said, you know, you shouldn't go
around being drunk. And
again as תוספות Tosafot points, אע"ג דליכא איסור af al gav de-leika
isur says תוספות, Tosafot, right? Even though you're not necessarily violating, but
you know, if you care about somebody and you care about how
they're acting and they're acting in an inappropriate way, you know, you
tell them about it in a loving way of course. So ותען
חנה ותאמר, Va-ta'an Hannah va-tomer, and Hannah responded and said, לא אדוני,
Lo Adoni, no my master. I'm not drunk. I am of anguished
soul and I'm pouring my heart out to God. אמר עולא ואיתימא
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Ulla ve-itima Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Hanina, אמר
ליה. amar lei. So she said to him, this phrase of אדוני,
Adoni, my master. לא אדון אתה בדבר זה. Lo adon atta ba-davar
zeh. You are not the master of this thing. You don't know
really what's going on. ולא רוח הקודש שורה עליך. Ve-lo Ruach HaKodesh
shora alecha. You are not, you don't have the divine, you know,
spirit here to understand what's going on. שאתה חושדני בדבר זה. She-atta
hoshedeni ba-davar zeh. You are suspecting me of this thing? You're suspecting
me of being drunk? I'm not drunk. I'm pouring out my heart
to God. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, הכי אמר ליה. hachi amar lei.
Some say this is what she said to him. לא אדון אתה.
Lo adon atta. You are not the אדון. Adon. You are not
God in a sense, like you don't know what's going on, you're
not the master, you're not an expert about this. You're saying who
do you think you are? You're not God. לאו איכא שכינה ורוח
הקודש גבך. Lav ika Shkhinah ve-Ruach HaKodesh gabach. It must be that
God's presence was not with you, שדנתני לכף חובה ולא דנתני לכף
זכות, she-dantani le-chaf chovah ve-lo dantani le-chaf zechut, that you would judge
me to the sort of to the scale, to the, not the
scale, what's it
called, the balance, what are those things called that you have on
the scale? What do you put the weight in? Those are the,
what? What are those called? The things you put the weight in.
Anyway, that's the כף. kaf. לכף חובה, Le-chaf chovah, it means like
literally like the hand or whatever, you know, those sort of scales,
right? Those balance scales. So when you see somebody doing something, you're
supposed to be, you know, you're supposed to judge them לכף זכות.
le-chaf zechut.
You're supposed to assume, tip the balance in their favor and assume
that what they're doing is proper rather than improper. So she said
you judged me. you're tipping in the improper, you assumed that I
was doing something wrong, ולא דנתני לכף זכות. velo dantaní le-chaf zechut.
You weren't judge me for the, for the scale, for tipping in
the favor of merit. מי לא ידעת, mi lo yadata, אשה קשת
רוח אנכי. isha keshat ruach anochi. Did you not know that I
was a woman of bitter of embittered soul, of anguished soul? יין
ושכר לא שתיתי. yayin veshichar lo shatiti.
I did not drink wine and mead. So therefore you did not
have God with you, you did not know what was going on.
And there is a very interesting הגה haga I have to tell
you, which is, he said how is it that עלי Eli made
a mistake? What does this mean? I mean he is a כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, he didn't have רוח הקדש? ruach ha-kodesh? So he
says and also he had the אורים ותומים urim vetumim which is
supposed to sort of give you direct messages from God. So he
says that the אורים ותומים, urim vetumim, the way they worked is
they had all the letters of the tribes inscribed on them. So
certain letters would sort of like rise up or appear before the
כהן kohen and it would be like the message from God. So
he said when חנה, Chana, the letters were ש shin כ chaf
ר resh ה, heh, so he saw it as שכורה, shikora, and
he didn't realize that
the message was supposed to be כשרה, keshera,
that she was like
שרה, Sarah, that she was barren and she was praying. Anyway, that's
a nice little ווארט vort of the הגר"א. ha-gra. It's not פשט,
pshat, but okay. Moving on. Anyway, she says you didn't know what
was going on, you were suspecting me that that was happening.
Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, מכאן לנחשד בדבר mikan le-nechshad
be-davar שאין בו. she-ein bo. So here we see that he was
giving her a little מוסר. mussar. He says you shouldn't go around
being drunk. But she in the end was innocent. So if you're
suspected of something that you're innocent about, שצריך להודיעו, she-tzarich lehodio, you
have to tell the person. Don't go around letting people think bad
things about you. If somebody suspected you incorrectly, you have to correct
them. Yes, she said no, I'm not drunk. אל
תתן את אמתך לפני בת בליעל. al titein et amatecha lifnei bat
beliyaal. Do not place your maidservant in front as a daughter, do
not treat her as a daughter of בליעל, beliyaal, like of some
irreligious person or some
what's a good translation of בליעל? beliyaal? What?
A non-believer?
Yeah, non-believer, right. Anyway, godless person maybe. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar
Rabbi Elazar, מכאן לשיכור שמתפלל כאילו עובד עבודה זרה. mikan le-shikor she-mitpalel
ke-ilu oved avodah zarah. Here you see that he, if she said
you were treating me like this sort of godless person or maybe
also thinking of the בעל, Baal, like the worshiper of the בעל
Baal is maybe a little part of the דרשה. drasha. So somebody
here it seems that if somebody דאוונס davens when they're drunk, it's
like they are עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. כתיב הכא ktiv
hacha לפני בת בליעל lifnei bat beliyaal וכתיב התם u-ktiv hatam יצאו
אנשים בני בליעל מקרבכם. yatzu anashim bnei beliyaal mikirbechem.
People of בליעל beliyaal came out of your midst and they led
the whole city to worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, these godless people.
So you see that that is what it's like if you're drunk.
Now why is it? It could just be because of the sense
that with the disrespect of God that you appear before God drunk,
it's as if you're עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah because it's
about your relationship with God. Could be more than that also, that
some types of forms of עבודה זרה avodah zarah were very much
about sort of getting drunk in the process, using these types of
artificial stimulants as a gaining some type of a heightened religious consciousness
or frenzy or so on. So that's why
you're כאילו עובד עבודה זרה ke-ilu oved avodah zarah if this is
the way you approach
דאווענינג.
davening. What? Ritual Bacchus?
Yeah, that's
true too. Right. ויען עלי ויאמר, vayaan Eli vayomar, so עלי Eli
said to her, לכי לשלום, lechi leshalom, go in peace.
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, מכאן לחושד את חברו בדבר mikan
le-choshed et chavero be-davar שאין בו, she-ein bo, שצריך לפייסו. she-tzarich le-fayeso.
Since we're talking about being suspected, so he suspected, he gave her
מוסר, mussar, she corrected him, now he finds out he made a
mistake. So you see that if you suspected somebody
and you were
being corrected, you have to appease them, you have to make peace
with them.
Okay, ולא עוד, velo od, אלא שצריך לברכו. ela she-tzarich le-varcho. Not
only that, you owe them a
ברכה. bracha. שנאמר shenemar ואלהי ישראל יתן את שלתך, velohei yisrael yitein
et sheilatecha, the God of Israel shall give your request. So when
we say before we learn out many הלכות, halachot, it's interesting the
הלכה halacha we learn out are not all הלכות halachot of תפלה.
tefillah. We actually really only learned out one or two הלכות halachot
of תפלה, tefillah, but we learn out many other הלכות halachot from
here as well, from the story of חנה Chana in terms of
seeing behavior that's perceived to be improper and so on. Now we
continue with this דרשה, drasha, ותדר נדר ותאמר, vatisdor neder vatomar, she
made a vow and she said, ה' צבאות, hashem tzevaot, Lord of
Hosts. So אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, מיום שברא הקדוש ברוך
הוא את עולמו, miyom she-bara hakadosh baruch hu et olamo, from the
day that God created the world, לא היה אדם שקרא להקדוש ברוך
הוא lo haya adam she-kara le-hakadosh baruch hu צבאות. tzevaot.
Nobody called God צבאות tzevaot which means like the heavenly host, like
צבא, tzava, like army, the heavenly host, עד שבאת חנה וקראה לו
צבאות, ad she-baata chana ve-karata lo tzevaot, until חנה Chana came along
and said called used the name of צבאות tzevaot referring to God.
אמרה חנה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amra chana lifnei hakadosh baruch hu,
חנה Chana said to God, רבונו של עולם, ribono shel olam, master
of the universe, מכל צבאי צבאות שבראת בעולמך, mikol tzevaei tzevaot she-barata
be-olamecha,
all of the hosts of hosts, all of the
universes and stars and galaxies and everything you created in your world,
קשה בעיניך שתתן לי בן אחד? kashe be-einecha she-titein li bein echad?
You with all of that, you can't give me one son?
So משל למה הדבר דומה, mashal lema hadavar domeh, now what is
this comparable to?
למלך בשר ודם שעשה סעודה לעבדיו, lemelech basar vadam she-asa seudah le-avadav,
a human king that made a feast for his servants. ובא עני
אחד ועמד על הפתח. uva ani echad ve-amad al hapetach. One poor
person came and stood by the doorway. אמר להם Amar lahem he
says to them, תנו לי פרוסה אחת Tenu li prusah achat said
please, you know, give me one little scrap of bread, ולא השגיחו
עליו Ve-lo hishgichu alav they didn't pay any attention to him. דחק
ונכנס אצל המלך Dachak ve-nichnas etzel ha-melech so the servants didn't pay
attention, so he forced his way into the king himself. אמר לו
Amar lo and said, אדוני המלך Adoni ha-Melech my master the king,
כל סעודה שעשית Kol se'udah she-asita oh, this entire lavish feast you
created, קשה בעיניך ליתן לי פרוסה אחת Kasheh be-einecha liten li prusah
achat
you can't give me one little scrap of bread? I have to
tell you, I don't exactly understand what the משל mashal added that
wasn't already pretty clear from the first way of saying it either,
but anyway. All right, so she says to God, God, how hard
is it for you to give me a son? אם ראה תראה
Im ra'oh tireh if you, you know, if you shall see with
the sort of, you know, the suffering of your maidservant.
So what is ראה תראה? ra'oh tireh? It's a double language.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, אמרה חנה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא,
amrah Chanah lifnei ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, Hannah said to God, ריבונו של
עולם Ribbono shel Olam master of
the universe, אם ראה im ra'oh if you
see, מוטב mutav good, you should see and you should answer me.
ואם לאו Ve-im lav and if you don't pay attention, you know,
sort of see my affliction, תראה tireh I will אסתרתר
בפני אלקנה בעלי estater bifnei Elkanah ba'ali
so I will... if you know if I do not appear before
you, then I will go and I will hide in front of,
you know, go in private with another man in the presence of
Elkanah my husband.
וכיון דמסתתרנא Ve-keivan de-mistatarna
and once I'm in private with another man, so he'll, you know,
if he goes to the whole סוטה sotah process, משקי לי מי
סוטה mashkei li mei sotah they'll make me drink the water, ואי
אתה עושה תורתך פלסתר ve-i atah oseh Torat-cha palaster and I'll sort
of force your hand because you will not make your Torah into
falsehood. פלסתר Palaster is an interesting Greek word, I forget does what's
his name say what it means there? Lie. What? Lie. Yeah, well,
I know it means like falsehood, but I wonder if... I assume
that Steinsaltz gives the actual sort of Greek for that? No.
No. פלסתר. Palaster.
Okay, no, nobody has it? Steinsaltz?
שקר וזיוף, Sheker ve-ziyuf, falsehood and
forgery.
Does he give a Greek for it? No. No, I assumed it
was Greek.
Yeah, he does. He does?
פלסטיק. Plastik.
Okay, is it from the similar word that we have for plastic?
No, I don't know.
The source's word is the Greek plastos
meaning a molder, a modeler, metaphorically in this context it means false.
Oh, a modeler, so maybe from the word plastic, no? Okay, interesting.
Okay. So you will not make your Torah like a forgery, a
falsehood, so I'm going to force an answer. שנאמר ונקתה ונזרעה זרע
shene'emar Ve-niktah ve-nizre'ah zara that a woman who is suspected and has
not committed adultery, she'll be cleansed and she will give forth seed,
which means that she will have children. So the גמרא Gemara now
says one minute, that's based on a מחלוקת. machloket. הניחא למאן דאמר
אם היתה עקרה נפקדת, Ha nicha le-man de-amar im hayta akara nifkedet,
שפיר, shapir, if according to the opinion that what happens with a
that's incorrectly suspected, that if she was barren she will become pregnant,
then it was good, it makes sense what Hannah was saying. אלא
למאן דאמר אם היתה יולדת בצער יולדת בריוח, Ela le-man de-amar im
hayta yoledet be-tza'ar yoledet be-revach, but according to the one that says
that if she was normally had pain in childbirth, she wouldn't actually,
a barren person would not actually become pregnant, fertile, but it means
that if she had children with pain, now she won't have childbirth
with pain. נקבות יולדת זכרים Nekevot yoledet zecharim if she had females,
she'll have males, assuming that males are the preferred children.
שחורים יולדת לבנים Shechorim yoledet levanim if the children were dark, now
they'll be light-skinned, fair-skinned, again assuming a certain preference there. קצרים יולדת
ארוכים Ketzarim yoledet aruchim if they were short, they'll be tall. Anyway,
so if it means not that barren will become pregnant and that's
not what will happen by the, so מאי איכא למימר mai ika
lemeimar how could you explain what Hannah did? דתניא De-tanya we taught
in the ברייתא braita this debate: ונקתה ונזרעה זרע Ve-niktah ve-nizre'ah zara
she'll be clean and she'll have seed, מלמד שאם היתה עקרה נפקדת
melamed she-im hayta akara nifkedet if she was barren she will have
children, דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei Rabbi Yishmael. That's what Rabbi Yishmael says.
אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva said to
him, אם כן ילכו כל העקרות כולן וייסתרו. im ken yelchu kol
ha-akarot kulan ve-yistatru. So he says, you know, they'll all figure this
out and then it'll be a great way for barren women to
become pregnant. They'll all go and they'll be go into private and
they'll go through this process in order to become pregnant. וזו שלא
קלקלה נפקדת Ve-zu she-lo kilkela nifkedet and a woman that did not
sin will, you know, or that, you know, is going to,
well, I guess the argument is נפקדת nifkedet will be, you know,
visited, meaning she will become pregnant. Of course it's not exactly clear
what the problem was with that, but you know, again, I guess
the point is you don't want to use the whole thing as
just a, you know, as a scheme and as a device for
becoming pregnant. אלא מלמד שאם היתה יולדת בצער יולדת בריוח Ela melamed
she-im hayta yoledet be-tza'ar yoledet be-revach so it's not that extreme that
barren becomes pregnant. It means that if it was childbirth with pain,
now it'll be with ease. קצרים יולדת ארוכים, Ketzarim yoledet aruchim, שחורים
יולדת לבנים, shechorim yoledet levanim, אחד יולדת שנים. echad yoledet shenayim. Interesting
it doesn't have, this version doesn't have male and female. Okay, short
would be long, black would be white. and only one child now
it'll be multiple births, so apparently those benefits are not so as
great as barren to becoming pregnant that we're not so much afraid
that it'll be the whole system will be manipulated and people will
play the system for that purpose.
Those are some incentives to that?
Right, exactly, but somehow maybe not as great. Anyway, מה אם ראות
תראה, Ma im ra'ot tireh, so what do you do now with
the פסוק, pasuk, since since she could not be saying I'm going
to force you to make me pregnant by doing this סוטה sotah
thing according to רבי עקיבא? Rabi Akiva? So דיברה תורה כלשון בני
אדם. Dibra Torah k'lishon bnei adam. Okay, that's just the normal way
in which people speak. The let's not overly interpret the double language
of ראות תראה. ra'ot tireh. Okay, keep on going. בעניי אמתך, B'oniy
amatcha, in the eyes or בעניי, b'oniy, excuse me, in the affliction
of your maidservant, if you will see God in the affliction of
your maidservant. So אל תשכח את אמתך, Al tishkach et amatcha, do
not forget your maidservant, sort of quoting different sections of her prayer.
ונתתה לאמתך, V'natata l'amatcha, and you shall give your maidservant a male
child, or whatever, a child. So it says three times אמתך. amatcha.
And the דרשה derasha here is not only going to be the
repetition of the word אמתך, amatcha, maidservant, but the word אמתך amatcha
almost has the word מיתה mita in it, death. So let's take
a look at what the דרשה derasha of the גמרא Gemara is.
אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Amar Rabi Yosi bar Chanina, ג' אמתות
הללו למה אמר, Gimel amtot halalu lama amar, why does it say
three times your maidservants? So אמרה חנה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amra
Chana lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so חנה Chana said to God, ריבונו
של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, Master of the Universe, שלושה בדקי מיתה
בראת באשה, Shlosha bidkei mita barata b'isha, three sort of a tests
of death You have created in a woman, ואמרי לה שלושה דפקי
מיתה, v'amrei lah shlosha difkei mita, three ways that death can cleave
to a woman. ואלו הן, V'elu hen, and these are: נדה וחלה
והדלקת הנר, niddah challah v'hadlakat haner, what we say in במה מדליקין,
Bameh Madlikin, say like ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, that there are three
that these three מצוות mitzvot are particularly seen as women's
mitzvot, the נדה, niddah, keeping of the menstrual laws, חלה challah is
taking of חלה challah and הדלקת הנר, hadlakat haner, the lighting of
the candle for ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, also these three very much
speak to sort of the sort of domestic sort of sense of
the woman in terms of the חלה, challah, the food, הדלקת הנר,
hadlakat haner, the house, the light of the house and so on.
Anyway, these three are seen that if a woman does not keep
them according to the משנה Mishna in במה מדליקין, Bameh Madlikin, that
then when she's in travail, so that will cause her
or childbirth, although that could bring about death. So חנה Chana says,
כלום עברתי על אחת מהן, Klum avarti al achat mehen, I didn't
do I never transgressed any one of these so therefore I've kept
all
of presumably my obligations and my מצוות mitzvot and therefore you should
answer my prayer. ונתתה לאמתך זרע אנשים, V'natata l'amatcha zera anashim, you
shall give to your maidservant a seed of people. What does that
mean? Wanted to say a child? מאי זרע אנשים, Mai zera anashim,
what does it mean a seed amongst people? So אמר רב גברא
בגוברין, Amar Rav gavra b'govrin, a man among men. What does that
mean? So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, tells us
basically it means like somebody that really is חשוב, chashuv, like somebody
who's a standout among other people. So that's what that's one answer.
ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, זרע שמושח שני אנשים. zera she'mosheach shnei anashim.
So the זרע zera and אנשים anashim is plural. A child, a
seed that will anoint two men. ומאן אינון, U'man inun, who are
they? שאול ודוד. Shaul v'David. Because her child was שמואל Shmuel and
he would then anoint as kings שאול Shaul and דוד. David. רבי
יוחנן אמר, Rabi Yochanan amar, זרע ששקול כשני אנשים, zera she'shakul k'shnei
anashim, a seed that is worthy, ששקול she'shakul as two other great
people. ומאן אינון, U'man inun, who are the two people that שמואל
Shmuel will be worthy of? משה ואהרן. Moshe v'Aharon. משה Moshe and
אהרן, Aharon, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, משה ואהרן בכהניו, Moshe v'Aharon b'chohanav, משה Moshe
and אהרן Aharon in their כהונה, kehuna, in their sort of service
attending of God, ושמואל בקוראי שמו, u'Shmuel b'korei shemo, and שמואל Shmuel
in the calling of the name. So שמואל Shmuel is equal to
משה Moshe and אהרן. Aharon. So you see he's balanced as equal
as these two great people. ורבנן אמרי, V'rabanan amri, so those answers
all speak about the greatness of שמואל. Shmuel. It's an interesting contrast
to the next interpretation, sort of the anonymous rabbis say, זרע אנשים
זרע שמובלע בין אנשים. zera anashim zera she'muvla bein anashim. Somebody that
is sort of like absorbed among people, does not stand out among
people. What does that mean? כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata
Rav Dimi amar, so רב דימי Rav Dimi explained: לא ארוך ולא
גוץ, lo aroch v'lo gutz, not too tall and not too short,
ולא קטן ולא אלם, v'lo katan v'lo ilem, not too thin, not
too fat, ולא צחור ולא גיחור, v'lo tzachor v'lo gichor, not too
ruddy, not too white, ולא חכם ולא טיפש, v'lo chacham v'lo tipesh,
not even not too smart and not too stupid. Average! Now what
does that mean? So first of all it's interesting that the people
that gave the explanation of average rather than outstanding were the anonymous
רבנן. Rabanan. Were the people that themselves maybe were not so outstanding
in terms of their own stature. But also it's interesting why to
be asking for that. So it could be that I think רש"י
Rashi says, what does רש"י Rashi say? שלא יהא תמה בין הבריות,
Shelo yehei tamah bein habriyot, and there shouldn't be an עין הרע.
ayin hara. Shouldn't be so outstanding that everybody gives him an עין
הרע. ayin hara. But it also could be just very much like
she's saying look, I just want a child. I'm not asking for
anything special. I don't need a superstar. Just give me a child.
Any child I'll be happy with. So it could just speak about
the poignancy of her request that it doesn't have to be special,
I just want a child. You wanted to say something, Charlie?
That ספרי Sifrei that they're quoting, had that been written at that
point?
Okay, no. But we neither had the מחלוקת machloket about רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael about סוטה, Sotah, so you
know, we're very, we play with time in these הגדות aggadot as.
Okay. So, so now it says like this:
אני האשה הנצבת עמך בזה. Ani ha'isha hanitzevet imcha bazeh. So then
the next year, right, when she had the child, she came back
to עלי Eli and she said, I was the woman who was
standing with you at this, you know, last year, this event.
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, מכאן שאסור
לישב, mikahn she'assur leshev, whatever it was in the past, I don't,
was not an issue next year anyway. Anyway, אמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
מכאן שאסור לישב בתוך ארבע אמות של תפילה. mikahn she'assur leshev betoch
arba amot shel tefilla. So you can't sit within ארבע אמות arba
amot of a person praying, because she said, I was standing with
you, so you also were standing, so you can't sit within the
ארבע אמות arba amot of a person praying. תוספות Tosafot says that
the דרשה drasha is also עמך imcha is spelled מלא malei with
a ה: hei: ע, מ, כ, ה. ayin, mem, chaf, hei. So
עמך, imcha, you can be in the ה, hei, in the fifth
אמה, amah, you can be sitting, but not within the first ארבע
אמות. arba amot. Now sometimes there's a problem that if you actually
sort of sit down, you know, people standing שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei,
somebody sits down next to you, the act of sitting down is
distracting, but also it could be that even if, you know, I'm
sitting and I'm doing something and you're standing, I'm sitting in your
ארבע אמות, arba amot, you're standing next to me in דאווענינג. davenning.
So if you take a look, תוספות Tosafot says that the problem
is not just the distraction issue, but the appropriateness issue. So תוספות
Tosafot here says, where is it, מכאן שאסור לישב בארבע אמות של
תפילה. mikahn she'assur leshev bearba amot shel tefilla. תוספות Tosafot says, בין
מלפניו בין מן הצדדים, bein milfanav bein min hatzedadim, whether in front
or by the
sides, ופירשו בתשובות גאונים דוקא ביושב ובטל, u-perashu beteshuvot geonim davka beyoshev
u-vatel, only if you're sitting and just like not doing anything.
אבל היה עוסק בקריאת שמע וברכות כיוצא בהן, Aval haya osek bikriat
shema u-berachot k'yotze bahen, if you're like a little דאווענינג, davenning, you're
saying קריאת שמע, Kriat Shema, then it's okay. So there it seems
to be the issue is not just my sitting next to you
as I'm distracting you, but if you're דאווענינג davenning and you're in
the presence of God, and that's like in the same space that
I'm inhabiting, I have to somehow, I can't be oblivious to that.
So I can't just be sitting and doing nothing. So if I
דאווען, daven, it's okay, but sitting and doing nothing when I'm sharing
the same space as that you are, you're דאווענינג, davenning, so the
problem is not my distracting you, but the inappropriateness of my behavior
just because I'm in your presence. What did you want to say
something, Charlie?
I was just saying that this is a problem in all the
crowded בתי כנסיות battei kenesiot we have.
I understand. So now you, but now with the תוספות'ס Tosafot's modification,
you have a little bit of an answer.
But would it, the same thing should include listening to חזרת הש"ץ,
Chazarat HaShatz, that it should be okay to sit if somebody behind
you is דאווענינג davenning שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esrei. Yeah, now there is a problem about going in front
of and like, you know, sort of moving in front of somebody.
If you're already there, and there's an issue between just sit, like
I said, sitting down, you know, there's one, here it's just being
in the space, not moving into the space. Moving into somebody's space
is a different concern. But if you're just in the space, like
a crowded שול, shul, and yes, then if you're sitting and participating
in חזרת הש"ץ, Chazarat HaShatz, that would not be a problem. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, אל הנער הזה התפללתי, el hana'ar
hazeh hitpallalti, I prayed for this child.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, שמואל, Shmuel, so the גמרא Gemara
makes an amazing הגדתא aggadta it reads into this story. שמואל מורה
הלכה לפני רבו היה. Shmuel moreh halacha lifnei rabbo hayah. שמואל Shmuel
actually פסקנ'ד paskened in front of his רבי, Rebbe, which is, as
we know, always bad news, right? According to one גמרא, Gemara, that
is what the sin
of נדב ואביהוא Nadav and Avihu was, that they פסקנ'ד paskened in
front of, you know, that's why they died because they were מורה
הלכה moreh halacha in the presence of משה. Moshe. שמואל Shmuel did
the same thing. Okay, how do you know this?
שנאמר וישחטו את הפר ויביאו את הנער אל עלי. Shene'emar vayishchatu et
hapar vayavi'u et hana'ar el Eli. They slaughtered the ox when they
went up, you know, when they brought שמואל Shmuel back, you know,
after he had been born, a few years after he'd been weaned,
and they brought the sacrifice of the ox and then they brought
שמואל Shmuel to עלי. Eli. So the גמרא Gemara says, what's the
juxtaposition? משום דוישחטו את הפר ויביאו את הנער אל עלי, Mishum de-vayishchatu
et hapar vayavi'u et hana'ar el Eli, they brought the
child to עלי, Eli, I mean, how are those two
connected? אלא אמר להם עלי, Ela amar lahem Eli, so עלי Eli
said when they brought the ox for sacrifice,
קראו כהן ויבא וישחט, kiru kohen ve-yavo ve-yishchat, go get a כהן,
kohen, we have a sacrifice, let him שחט shecht the cow.
The ox, anyway, ויבא וישחט. ve-yavo ve-yishchat. חזייה שמואל דהוה קא מהדר
בתר כהן למישחט. Chazei'u Shmuel d'hava ka-mehadir batar kohen l'mishchat. שמואל, Shmuel,
who how old was he at that time, anyway, three years old,
five years old, he saw that they were looking for a כהן
kohen to bring to שחט shecht the cow. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
so he said to the people around
him, למה לכון להדורי בתר כהן למישחט שחיטה בזר כשרה. lamah lachun
l'hadurei batar kohen l'mishchat shechita be-zar kesherah. We know that a non-כהן
kohen can שחט shecht for a
קרבן. korban. אייתיוה לקמיה דעלי, Ayytayu lekameh d'Eli, so they brought him
in front of עלי, Eli, which is funny because it sounds like
they were all right there at the same moment because he was
getting a cow for the people, anyway, and if he was being
פסקנ'ד paskened in front of עלי. Eli. So anyway, but somehow they
presented him then to עלי. Eli. אמר
ליה, Amar leh, so עלי Eli said to him, מנא לך הא,
mina lach ha, I heard you were telling the, you know, your
parents not to bother with a כהן, kohen, how do you know
this? So אמר ליה, amar leh, מי כתיב ושחט הכהן? mi ketiv
ve-shachat hakohen? It doesn't say the כהן kohen shall slaughter in ויקרא
Vayikra where it talks about bringing a קרבן. korban. והקריבו הכהנים, ve-hikrivu
hakohenim, it says the כהנים kohanim will bring the blood. So they
start after they caught the blood.
They start when they catch the blood. מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה, Mikabala
ve’eilech mitzvat kehunah, they start when they catch the blood. מכאן דשחיטה
כשרה בזר, Mikan d’shechitah kesherah be’zar, so anything before that, you don’t
need a כהן. Cohen. A non-כהן Cohen can do it. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, it's a good thing, Erchal, by the way, he
didn't quote a משנה. Mishnah. He
quoted a פסוק. Pasuk. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, מימר שפיר קאמרת,
meimar shapir kamart, you said good, it's right, it's a good point,
you're right, you can get a non-כהן Cohen to שחט. shecht. מיהו,
Mihu, but however, מורה הלכה בפני רבך. moreh halacha bifnei ravcha. There's
a little other problem
which is you're paskening in front of your רבי. Rebbe. וכל המורה
הלכה בפני רבו, V'kol hamoreh halacha bifnei rabbo, anybody who paskens in
front of their רבי, Rebbe, חייב מיתה, chayav misa, deserves a form
of death. So אתיא חנה, atya Chana, so she came, so חנה
Chana came, right, וקצוחה קמיה v'katzcha kamei and was crying out in
front of עלי. Eli. אני האשה הנצבת עמך בזה, Ani ha'isha hanitzevet
imcha bazeh, I was the one that was standing before you those
years back and prayed for this child. אמר לה, Amar lah, so
he said to
חנה, Chana, שבקי לי דאקטליה, shivki li d'aktlei, let me give him
the punishment he deserves, call on God I guess to kill him,
ובעינא רחמי, u'beina rachamei,
I'll pray to God, ויהיב לך רבא מיניה, v'yahiv lach raba minei,
I'll give you a better son than this, I'll replace him with
a better son. אמרה ליה, Amra lei, so she says to him,
אל הנער הזה התפללתי, el hana'ar hazeh hitpalalti, I prayed for this
child. Don't tell me you're going to give me another child. This
is my child, this is the one I prayed for. So all
of that was a דרשה drasha on the word of הזה. hazeh.
But it's interesting, it does a little bit play off the earlier
דרשה drasha about that like, I'm not asking for special, I just
want a child. Don't think you can exchange, I'll get a better
one, it's my child, this is the one I want. So somehow
he got out of being punished. Now תוספות Tosafot says interesting, what
do you mean that עלי Eli was his רבי? Rebbe? This was
the first time he was being brought to עלי. Eli. So תוספות
Tosafot says
ואף על פי שלא למד עדיין בפניו, v'af al pi shelo lamad
adayin befanav, he right, מכל מקום גדול הדור היה, mi'kol makom gadol
hador haya, ובא ללמוד לפניו. u'ba lilmod lefanav. So עלי Eli was
still the גדול הדור gadol hador and since he was going to
be learning by עלי, Eli, he already had the status of his
רבי Rebbe and he couldn't pasken in front of him.
The fact that he was six years old has nothing to do
with it.
Right. Right, we're not talking
about a human court, sort of divine deserving. I know the whole
thing is fascinating. We do, we do. I mean he was young.
It's I think it says right after he was weaned, right? Correct.
Does say that. I'm just looking, yeah, yeah, yeah.
You're saying that עלי Eli recognized this child as a
genius and he's going to I'll take him under my wing. Right.
But she says she wants only she doesn't care if the other
child is this child and she wants to raise it.
Exactly. Now part of it also could be playing because the story
right afterwards right has that he was sleeping there in the environment
of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and he hears God's voice and
God's calling שמואל Shmuel and עלי Eli doesn't hear it. So the
story right afterwards does
happen obviously sort of exceeding עלי Eli and eclipsing עלי, Eli, so
maybe it's a little bit of evoking that sense as well. Yes.
I mean who remembers עלי Eli anyway?
I mean we know about שמואל, Shmuel, right?
People tend to forget about עלי. Eli. Yeah.
Yes.
But what's interesting first of all he's three years old, he's not
חייב chayav for anything.
I know that was the point before.
And the second thing is we have a woman in the עזרה.
azarah.
Ah yeah, that's true.
Although we did have the formal בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash for that
too. וחנה היא מדברת על לבה, V'Chana hi medaberet al libah, Chana
was speaking on her heart. So going back to the
earlier פסוקים, pesukim, אמר רבי אלעזר משום רבי יוסי בן זמרא, amar
Rabbi Elazar mishum Rabbi Yosei bin Zimra, על עסקי לבה, al iskei
libah, regarding matters of her heart. And let's see we don't just
mean her feelings and her intent, let's see what it says. אמרה
לפניו, Amra lefanav, she said to God, רבונו של עולם, Ribono shel
Olam, Master of the Universe, כל מה שבראת באשה לא בראת דבר
אחד לבטלה, kol mah shebarata b'ishah lo barata davar echad levatalah,
whatever you created for by a woman and of anybody thing was
not for naught. עינים לראות, Einayim lirot, you've given me eyes to
see, ואזנים לשמוע, v'oznayim lishmoa, ears to hear, חוטם להריח, chotem l'hariach,
a nose to smell, פה לדבר, peh l'daber, mouth to speak, ידים
לעשות בהם מלאכה, yadayim la'asot bahem melachah, hands to do
work with, רגלים להלך בהם, raglayim l'halech bahem,
feet to walk with, דדים להניק בהם, dadim l'hanik bahem, and breasts
to suckle a child, to nurse a child. דדים הללו שנתת על
לבי, Dadim elalu shenatata al libi, these breasts you've given me on
my heart, that's על לבה, al libah, למה, lamah, why have you
given them to me? לא להניק בהם, Lo l'hanik bahem, not that
I should be able to nurse a child? תן לי בן ואניק
בהם, Ten li ben v'anik bahem, so give me a child so
that I should nurse by them. Which is I think it's very
poignant the sense of not being able to have a child, what
that could
mean for a woman not being able to do that most basic
sort of biological thing that women's bodies are made for.
ואמר רבי אלעזר משום רבי יוסי בן זמרא, V'amar Rabbi Elazar mishum
Rabbi Yosei bin Zimra, כל היושב בתענית בשבת, kol hayoshev b'ta'anit b'Shabbat,
anybody now this has nothing to do with anything but we mentioned
Rabbi Elazar in the name of Rabbi Yosei bin Zimra. So anybody
who sits in a תענית ta'anit on שבת, Shabbos, and תוספות Tosafot
says and the גאונים Geonim say it means because of a תענית
חלום, ta'anit chalom, that you had a very disturbing dream and the
idea is that you're supposed to fast immediately the next day even
if it's שבת. Shabbos. So if you do that, קורעין לו גזר
דינו של שבעים שנה, kora'in lo gzar dino shel shiv'im shanah, even
if you had an evil decree written against you in heaven 70
years old it's been standing very sort of... heavy decree, it'll be
torn up if you are willing to fast when you need to
on שבת *Shabbos*. As רש"י rashi *Rashi* says, it's very hard, everybody
else is having nice food, and you know, it's being so and
having a good time, and here you are fasting.
If it was seventy years old?
I mean, that the גזירה
*gzira* would last for seventy years?
I didn't understand that. I thought it meant that you've been sort
of in God's bad books for the last seventy years. That's the
way I understood it. Anyway, רש"י rashi. *Rashi* says, אפילו נגזרה עליו
מנעוריו *afilu nigzara alav mine'urav*, even if it's been a גזירה *gzira*
from the time you've been young. Anyway, ואף על פי כן *v'af
al pi chein*, so therefore they will tear it up. ואף על
פי כן כופין אותו להתענות עוד פעם אחת בשבת *v'af al pi
chein kofin oso l'his'anos od pa'am achas b'Shabbos*, but nevertheless, you're going
to have to accept a certain slap and punishment for having not
done the מצוה *mitzvah* of having pleasure of שבת *Shabbos*, of עונג
שבת *oneg Shabbos*. So you do it and it's necessary and it's
very effective, but there still is another little problem that results from
it. מאי תקנתיה *mai takantei*, so how do you fix that problem
of having missed עונג שבת *oneg Shabbos*? So אמר amar רב נחמן
בר יצחק ליתיב תעניתא לתעניתא *amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak leisiv tanisa
l'tanisa*. We don't say do a double עונג שבת *oneg Shabbos* next
week, do a fast for having done a fast. Somehow that fixes
up the עונג שבת *oneg Shabbos*. All right, so we're just going
to move on after that, that was a little bit of a
digression. ואמר רבי אלעזר חנה הטיחה דברים כלפי מעלה *v'amar Rabbi Elazar
Chana hiticha devarim klapei ma'ala*. So now, what's interesting to note about
all of this is as you can see by the דפי *dafi*
we just read, the י' דף daf *yud daf* that's coming, there's
a lot of אגדתא *agadata*. But as you know, Dov said beforehand,
I think that the גמרא gemara *Gemara* really, it's not just sometimes
the גמרא gemara. *Gemara* just has an opportunity for אגדתא *agadata*, but
here it's about a פרק perek *perek* which starts about כוונה *kavana*
and how do you sort of see the models of how people
prayed, which is, you know, can serve for models for us. So
you know, so by elaborating on it, it's interesting in terms of
creating certain types of models. So until now, what we've had with
חנה *Chana* in terms of the models, you know, was a little
bit of sort of making demand, you know, sort of finding ways
to sort of push God a little, which is fascinating, you know,
in terms of the just total, you know, abnegation of self. She
was saying you'd better see and if not I'm going to manipulate
it and she's, you know, a little bit of demanding, why have
you created my body like this, not to have
children, right? I've done all the מצוות *mitzvos* I'm supposed to do.
So there's a little sense of like, you know, of like not
just complete I'm nothing, I'm worthless, please give it to me like
a begging. There's a certain sense of like a little push, you
know, and so it's important to think about what model we're being
presented with, which you don't get from פסוקים pesukim, *psukim*, right? You
read the פסוקים pesukim *psukim*, you don't get that sense, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* read into it. And now we actually
take that, you know, a little bit further. So let's
take a look.
So it says חנה *Chana*, yes,
that may be when you said before you didn't see what the
story was about when this poor person came? Yeah. So the poor
person had to push his way in.
Oh, that's interesting. The image of forcing your way in to get
to the king. That's a nice point. Okay. Right. And the whole
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about, right, the ה' צבאות *Hashem Tzevaot* that you
have everything, why can't you give me this?
ה' דף daf. ומחצה *hei daf u'mechtza* we had an example where
they just let the doors in.
Right, right. Okay. So that's anyway, so until now we have her
being a little, a little like demanding, which is interesting that this
is the model we're being presented with and now let's see, the
גמרא *Gemara* takes it further. ואמר רבי אלעזר חנה הטיחה דברים כלפי
מעלה *v'amar Rabbi Elazar Chana hiticha devarim klapei ma'ala*. She sort of
like, sort of cast her words up to God. She sort of
almost was, you know, sort of attacking almost, or whatever, you know,
very strong, aggressive. שנאמר she'ne'emar, ותתפלל על ה' *shene'emar vatitpalel al Hashem*,
not אל ה' *el Hashem* to God, but על ה' *al Hashem*
on God, like against God. מלמד שהטיחה דברים כלפי מעלה *melamed shehiticha
devarim klapei ma'ala*. She sort of, you know, plastered her words, slapped,
you know, threw her words to God. ואמר רבי אלעזר אליהו הטיח
דברים כלפי מעלה *v'amar Rabbi Elazar Eliyahu hitich devarim klapei ma'ala*. Not
just חנה *Chana*, אליהו *Eliyahu*, שנאמר she'ne'emar, ואתה הסבות את לבם אחורנית
*shene'emar v'ata hasibos es libam achoranis*. אליהו *Eliyahu* says God, you made
their hearts sort of turn away from you, blaming God for it.
God, it's your fault. So אמר רבי שמואל בר יצחק מנין שחזר
הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu והודה לאליהו *amar Rabbi Shmuel bar
Yitzchak minayin shechazar HaKadosh Baruch Hu v'hoda l'Eliyahu*? Where do you see
that God went back and conceded to אליהו *Eliyahu* that to some
degree God was to blame? דכתיב ואשר הרעותי *dech'siv v'asher hareiosi*. So
this is not by אליהו *Eliyahu*, it's by מיכה *Micha*, but it
says and that I have caused them to do evil. God takes
responsibility to some degree that for creating this יצר הרע *yetzer hara*
that we have an inclination to do evil.
So now we're going to focus on this, on the fact that,
you know, that we don't always, we are created in ways that
we don't always have the strength to withstand our temptation. So let's
take a look. But again, the theme here still is about חנה
*Chana* and really sort of a little bit of, you know, sort
of like being, you know, sort of pushing her case before God.
So I'm at so top of ל"ב עמוד amud א' *lamed bais
amud aleph*, אמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא אלמלא שלש מקראות הללו *amar
Rabbi Chama b'rebi Chanina ilmala shalosh mikra'os elalu*, were it not for
the following three verses, נתמוטטו רגליהם של שונאי ישראל Yisrael. *nismotitu ragleihem
shel sonei Yisrael*, the legs of the literally haters of Israel, that's
a euphemism for the Jewish people, would have been sort of collapsed,
would have been weakened. We would have,
meaning we would have fallen. חד דכתיב ואשר הרעותי *chad dech'siv v'asher
hareiosi*, God admits, 'I have done evil,' meaning I've created in them
the evil inclination, I take some responsibility. וחד דכתיב *v'chad dech'siv*, one
verse says, הנה כחומר ביד היוצר *hinei k'chomer b'yad hayotzer*, right, coming
up to the ימים נוראים *Yamim Noraim*, behold as the clay in
the hand of the potter. כן אתם בידי בית ישראל Yisrael. *kein
atem beyadi Beis Yisrael*. So are you in my hands, oh children
of Israel. Now you could say this means God determines our fate,
but it also means that God has created us and presumably maybe
there's a דרשה *drasha* here of also יוצר *yotzer* and יצר *yeitzer*,
right, God has also created in us
the evil inclination. וחד דכתיב *vechad dichtiv* and one says והסירותי את
לב האבן מבשרכם ונתתי לכם לב בשר *vahasirosi es lev ha'even mivsarkhem
venasasi lakhem lev basar* I will remove from you the heart of
stone and I will give you a heart of flesh. So if
God is to give us a heart of flesh right now and
he's not giving it to us right now, so to some degree
it's because of how we've been created that we can't always do
what is correct. רב פפא אמר מהכא *Rav Papa amar meihakha* from
the following verse ואת רוחי אתן בקרבכם ועשיתי את אשר בחוקותי תלכו
*ve'es ruchi etein bekirbekhem ve'asisi es asher bechukosai teileikhu* I will give
my spirit in
you and I will make it that you will walk in my
paths. So again, meaning that that's something that you could do right
now, so again it is not, it is partly that you had
created us this way. ואמר רבי אלעזר משה Moshe הטיח דברים כלפי
מעלה *ve'amar Rabbi Elazar Moshe hitiach devarim klapei ma'alah*. Now getting back
to the main theme about people who in their prayer are really
like a little bit sort of challenging God or sort of pointing
a finger to God: God, it's partly your fault. So Moshe did
it as well שנאמר sene'emar ויתפלל משה Moshe אל השם *shene'emar vayispaleil
Moshe el Hashem* Moshe prayed to God. אל תקרי אל השם אלא
על השם *al tikrei el Hashem ela al Hashem* to God against
God. Okay, so that's funny because where do you get that you
could have anytime it says על השם *al Hashem* שכן דבי רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב קורין לאלפין עיינין ולעיינין אלפין *shekein debei Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov korin le'alfin ayinin ule'ayinin alfin*. And the house of רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* they call an א *aleph*
sounds like an ע *ayin* and an ע *ayin* an א *aleph*.
הגמרא *Hagemara* says this elsewhere actually, it's quite interesting because it actually
speaks about, I think, in בית שאן *Beis Shean* and by רבי
*Rebbi* because it has to do with
sort of the Greek and Hellenistic sort of cult influence or whatever
as opposed to
the Mediterranean one which has the or Middle Eastern one which has
the guttural letters. Nowadays most אשכנזים *Ashkenazim* pronounce עיינין *ayinin* like אלפין
*alfin*, right, because we don't have guttural sounds in our language. So
the גמרא *Gemara* actually there's another גמרא *Gemara* that's even clearer that
it had to do with, I think if I remember correctly it
mentions specifically בית שאן *Beis Shean* which was a very Hellenistic city,
very cosmopolitan, not all Jewish and so on. So it speaks about
the losing of the guttural sounds. Anyway, so אל השם *el Hashem*,
על השם *al Hashem*, basically the same thing. Alright, that's not the
greatest proof. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי מהכא *amrei debei Reb Yannai meihakha*
from here ודי זהב *Vedi Zahav* which is in the beginning of
דברים *Devarim*, right, where it speaks of Moshe said these words and
mentions this place ודי זהב *Vedi Zahav*. What is that place? So
מאי ודי זהב *mai Vedi Zahav*? אמרי דבי רבי ינאי *amrei debei
Reb Yannai* famous דרשה *drasha* that רש״י *Rashi* quotes כך אמר משה
לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא amar moshe lifnei hakadosh baruch hu *kach amar
Moshe lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu*. This is what Moshe said to God
ריבונו של עולם ribono shel olam *Ribono Shel Olam* Master of the
Universe בשביל כסף וזהב שהשפעת להם לישראל *bishvil kesef vezahav shehishpata lahem
leYisrael* because ודי זהב *Vedi Zahav* is like די זהב *dai zahav*
too much enough gold. Because of the gold and silver that you
sort of overflowed onto them, the ישראל *Yisrael* עד שאמרו די *ad
she'amru dai* until they said enough, enough. הוא גרם שעשו את העגל
*hu garam she'asu es ha'eigel*. That caused them to make the calf.
They had so much gold they were looking for trouble. It was
just asking for trouble. It's your fault, God. Which is interesting, which
is not just your fault until now, it's been more like you
created us with the types of desires and human weaknesses, but here
it's also the circumstances that you put them in that caused them
to sin as well. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי *amrei debei Reb Yannai*
they say in the house of רבי ינאי *Reb Yannai* some very
powerful I think metaphors here in the גמרא *Gemara* about the truth
of this statement. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי *amrei debei Reb Yannai* they
say in the house of רבי ינאי *Reb Yannai* אין ארי נוהם
מתוך קופה של תבן אלא מתוך קופה של בשר *ein ari noheim
mitoch kupah shel teven ela mitoch kupah shel basar*. The lion does
not roar when he's eating a sort of a trough of a
box of a
straw, only if he's after he's had a nice meat of devouring
an animal of flesh then he roars. When you're a little bit
have too much good and you feel too good about yourself then
you're going to start looking for trouble.
Then if things are a little bit more austere then you'll stay
on the straight and narrow. אמר רבי אושעיא משל לאדם שהיתה לו
פרה כחושה ובעלת איברים *amar Rabbi Oshaya mashal le'adam shehayesa lo parah
khushah uva'alas eivarim*. A person had a weak cow and it like
has its limbs sticking out, visible limbs. האכילה כרשינין *he'ekhilah karshinin* and
he fed it כרשינין *karshinin* which is some type of a nice
grain that usually is reserved more for humans והיתה מבעטת בו *vehayesa
meva'ates bo* and then it started rebelling and kicking. אמרו לו מי
גרם לך שתהא מבעטת בי אלא כרשינין שהאכלתיך *amru lo mi garam
lach shetehei meva'ates bi ela karshinin shehe'ekhaltikh*. What caused you to kick
against me?
It must be these כרשינין *karshinin* whatever they are some type of
a grain that I fed you. So again, you get you make
somebody a little too fat, too satisfied, feels too haughty, and that
leads to acting out. אמרי דבי רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan, משל לאדם אחד שהיה לו בן *amrei debei
Reb Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan mashal le'adam echad shehayah lo
bein*. They say in the house of רבי חייא בר אבא *Reb
Chiyya bar Abba* רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said there's a very famous
משל *mashal* gets quoted other places. A person had a son שרחצו
וסכו והאכילו *sherichatzo vesakho vehe'ekhilo*. He bathed him, he anointed, he rubbed
him with oil, made him feel very special, spoiled him essentially. This
is what happens when you spoil kids. והאכילו *vehe'ekhilo* and he fed
him... והאכילו והשקהו, gave him food and drink, ותלה כיס בצוארו, v'tala
kis b'tzavaro, put around his neck a like a you know a
purse filled with money, והושיבו אפתח של זונות, v'hoshivo a'petach shel zonot,
and put him right by the brothel. Okay, so מאי יעשה אותו
בן שלא יחטא? mai ya'aseh oto ben shelo yecheta? What do you
want the kid to do and not to sin? Okay, you're giving
him all of the opportunity and you're making him feel very entitled.
So that's what you did, you gave them all this gold and
you ask what are they supposed to do if not sin? אמר
רב אחא בריה דרב הונא אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Acha brei
d'Rav Huna amar Rav Sheshet, היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi, that's
what people say, מלי כריסיה זני בישא, malei kerisei zanei bisha, a
full stomach is bad news. It's basically like you know of a
bad type, Rashi says, or bad
sins, שנאמר, כמרעיתם וישבעו, k'mar'itam vayisbau, when they sort of grazed and
they sated, שבעו וירם לבם, sav'u vayaram libam, they were sated and
their heart grew haughty. על כן שכחוני, al ken shechechuni, therefore they
have forgotten me. רב נחמן אמר מהכא, Rav Nachman amar me'hacha, from
the following verse. I mean these are clear פסוקים, pesukim ורם לבבך,
v'ram levavecha, your heart will grow haughty, ושכחת את השם אלוקיך, v'shachachta
et Hashem Elokecha, and you'll forget Hashem your God. רבנן אמרי מהכא,
Rabanan amri me'hacha, ואכל ושבע ודשן, v'achal v'sava v'dashen, they will eat
and be satisfied and be fat, ופנה, u'fana, and then they'll turn
to other gods. ואי בעית אימא מהכא, v'i bayit eima me'hacha, if
you want from here, וישמן ישורון ויבעט, vayishman Yeshurun vayivat, Jeshurun Israel
grew fat and they kicked, they rebelled. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, מנין
שחזר הקדוש ברוך הוא והודה לו למשה? minayin shechazar HaKadosh Baruch Hu
v'hoda lo l'Moshe? And how do you know the הקדוש ברוך הוא
agreed to Moshe because
we've
been quoting so many פסוקים pesukim about having it good and rebelling?
It's starting to also sound like you know we're being blamed, which
a lot of those פסוקים pesukim are, are blaming us for having
forgotten God when it got good. But the theme here was that
God also has to share in the responsibility. So how do you
know that God went back and agreed to Moshe? שנאמר, it says,
וכסף הרביתי להם וזהב עשו לבעל, v'chesef hirbeiti lahem v'zahav asu la'ba'al,
I've given them, I gave them much
silver and gold and they took the gold and they made it
for the Baal for this, you know, for these false gods. Okay,
so again this was quite fascinating because now what it is saying
that part of the sort of you know prayer, again thinking about
the models of prayer, it's amazing here in a דף and a
half, an עמוד and a half, the models of prayer have been
like pretty aggressive, like pretty like you know coming to God with
a טענה, ta'ana, like you know it's like the stories about who
was it, the Chassidic Rebbe that was sort of always like the
defender of Israel, what you know who that one is? Yeah, רבי
לוי יצחק מברדיטשוב, Rabbi Levi Yitzchak m'Berditchev, right, you know, exactly. So
God, here's my טענה, ta'ana, you have to answer. You know, so
we were having that by Chana before, like how hard would it
be for you God? And here it's like what, if I wasn't
perfect, okay you know, the circumstances that you put me in, there's
the way you created me. So again, it's not to get us
totally off the hook, but again there's a, it's quite fascinating that
this in the beginning of the פרק is what's being held up
as the model for תפילה. tefillah. Okay, so now the Gemara continues,
וידבר השם אל משה, Vayidaber Hashem el Moshe, Moshe Hashem spoke to
Moshe, לך רד, lech red, go down. Right now we're talking about
Moshe, you know, and the חטא העגל chet ha'egel and it's partly
God's fault. So now we're going to look at the חטא העגל.
chet ha'egel. Go down quickly. מאי לך רד? mai lech red? What
does it mean go, you know, go down? אמר רבי אלעזר אמר
לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar lo HaKadosh Baruch
Hu l'Moshe, God said to Moshe, רד מגדולתך, red mi'gedulatecha, maybe they're
reading it also like לך רד, lech red, you know you should
go down. It's a going down for you, you have to descend
from your height, from your status. כלום נתתי לך גדולה אלא בשביל
ישראל? klum natati lecha gedulah ela bishvil Yisrael? I only gave you
this status because of Israel. ועכשיו ישראל חטאו, v'achshav Yisrael chatu,
now they've sinned and they've lost their status, אתה למה לי? ata
lama li? what do I need you for? which is quite fascinating
because it's again the פסוקים pesukim which says ואעשה אותך לגוי גדול
ועצום, v'e'eseh otcha l'goy gadol v'atzum, right, so the פסוקים psukim are
all like oh God likes Moshe, He's willing to do away with
ישראל. But the מדרש midrash here flips it, like God really only
primarily cares about ישראל. Moshe's just the leader, but he's a leader
because of the people, because God's concern is for the people. So
again, it's fascinating how this little מדרש midrash completely undermines like you
know the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim to focus on the
concern for the people. מיד תשש כחו של משה, miyad tashash kocho
shel Moshe,
Moshe's strength was weakened. ולא היה לו כח לדבר, v'lo haya lo
koach l'daber, he couldn't respond, he didn't know what to say. Okay,
because he couldn't even respond as we're going to see to defend
the people. He was basically sort of you know kicked out. So
once he's kicked out, he feels he doesn't even have a place
to say anything. וכיון שאמר, v'keivan she'amar, but then God said to
me, הרף ממני ואשמידם, heref mimeni v'ashmidem, leave me and I will
destroy them, let go of me and I will destroy them. אמר
משה דבר זה תלוי בי, amar Moshe davar zeh talui bi, oh
I see that I can actually do something. God says He needs
me to leave Him alone so He can destroy them, that means
I can play a role. מיד עמד ונתחזק בתפילה, miyad amad v'nitchazek
b'tefillah,
then he strengthened himself in prayer. ביקש רחמים, bikesh rachamim, and he
asked compassion from God. משל למלך שכעס על בנו, mashal l'melech sheka'as
al beno, like a king who got angry for a son, והיה
מכהו מכה גדולה, v'haya makehu makah gedolah, and the son was like
you know hitting the son with a you know really sort of
vigorously, והיה אוהבו יושב לפניו, v'haya ohavo yoshev lefanav, and the king's
you know sort of favorite or somebody, the counselor was right there
right. right in the front of the king, the close friend, ומצטער
לומר לו דבר u'mitsta'er lomar lo davar I can't say anything, I
mean the king is punishing his son, what am I supposed to
do? He was afraid for himself, and so אמר המלך amar hamelech
and then the king said, אלמלי אלמלי almalei almalei אוהבי זה שיושב
לפניי ohavi ze sheyoshev lefanai הרגתיך הרגתיך, hargaticha hargaticha,
if it were not that my friend was sitting right here I
would have killed you. So אמר so he was sending a message
a not so hidden message to the friend, אתה בז על כבודי
ata baz al kvodi oh I see that the king cares about
what I say and my presence. מיד עמד והצילו miyad amad v'hetsilo
so then the friend intervened and saves. So once Moshe saw that
he had a place, הרף ממני heref mimeni Moshe was able to
intervene. So again it's sort of showing about how God sent Moshe
this message that he wanted Moshe to intervene but and why Moshe
initially was silent until that, but also this idea of Moshe's status,
God really cares primarily about Israel, Moshe's status was for the sake
of Israel. So by the way I should also say that we've
now also seen three different types of prayer sort of for what
purpose, meaning here there's a prayer because you desperately are in need
of something, right? You want for your son. Here there is an
הכרת חטא hakarat chet about sort of our sin and praying presumably
some sense about forgiveness or acknowledging our sin, praying to God I
mean that was implicit although it didn't say that explicitly, right? And
here, you know, it's sort of praying either for yourself or for
some somebody else but to save from suffering, right, or from punishment
and so on. So it's also interesting how the roles play or
is playing in addition to sort of the way one is praying.
Okay, ועתה הניחה לי v'ata haniicha li so God says to Moshe,
leave me alone, ויחר אפי בהם ואכלם v'yichar api bahem v'achalem
my anger will burn against them and I will and I will
destroy them, ואעשה אותך לגוי גדול v'e'eseh otcha l'goy gadol I'll make
you into a great nation. אמר רבי אבהו amar rabbi avahu אלמלא
מקרא כתוב אי אפשר לאמרו almalei mikra katuv i efshar l'omro were
it not in a verse you would not be able to say
such a thing. מלמד שתפס משה להקדוש ברוך הוא melamed she'tafas moshe
l'hakadosh baruch hu כאדם שתופס את חבירו בבגדו k'adam she'tofes et chaveiro
bivigdo Moshe
like grabbed God by the shirt, by the collar, like a person
that would grab his friend by his by his cloak, right, ואמר
לפניו v'amar lefanav and said before Him, ריבונו של עולם ribono shel
olam אין אני מניחך עד שתמחול ותסלח להם ein ani manichacha ad
she'timchol v'tislach lahem I won't leave You until You forgive them, like
grabbing him by the collar. So because הניחה לי haniicha li God
says leave me, let go of me. So it's as if Moshe
in his prayer was grabbing God by the collar. Again, a very
powerful image in terms of the potential power of our prayer. You
know, if although Moshe, I mean nobody thinks for Moshe, but if
you see about and that you have the פסוקים right I mean
my God the פסוקים are about Moshe, speaks to the power of
prayer, Moshe's prayer saves כלל ישראל. klal yisrael. So this is גמרא
obviously just even that much more sort of, you know, sort of
underscores that by this image of Moshe holding onto God as it
were. ואעשה אותך לגוי גדול v'e'eseh otcha l'goy gadol I'll make you
into a great nation. אמר רבי אלעזר amar rabbi elazar so Rabbi
Elazar, אמר משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא amar Moshe lifnei HaKadosh Baruch
Hu
this is what Moshe responded to God when God said I'll make
you into a great nation. ריבונו
של עולם Master of the Universe, ומה כיסא של שלוש רגליים אינו
יכול לעמוד u'mah kisei shel shalosh raglayim eino yachol la'amod if a
chair of three legs can't stand which is אברהם יצחק ויעקב avraham
yitzchak v'yaakov לפניך בשעת כעסך lefanacha b'sha'at ka'ascha when You get angry,
that's not enough, the זכות אבות, zechut avot, כיסא של רגל אחת
על אחת כמה וכמה kisei shel regel achat al achat kama v'chama
if You make me into a nation there'll only be one leg
to stand on my זכות, zechut, how much more so will they
be in trouble if they ever if they ever anger You. ולא
עוד אלא שיש בי בושת פנים מאבותיי v'lo od ela she'yesh bi
boshet panim me'avotai I'll be embarrassed from from my my parents or
my
forefathers. Now why? שמעכשיו יאמרו ראו פרנס שהעמיד עליהם she'me'achshav yomru re'u
parnas she'he'emid aleihem look at this sort of leader, פרנס parnas also
very much evokes the type of word they had for leaders in
the time of the גמרא. So like this, you know, sort of
communal leader that they that God put up over them, ביקש גדולה
לעצמו ולא ביקש עליהם רחמים bikeish gedulah l'atsmo v'lo bikeish aleihem rachamim
he was totally happy to be made into the top guy and
to get, you know, and to get all of this status and
honor and he did not see that his primary role was to
protect the people. So it's the same idea like even though God
is saying to Moshe I'll focus on you, Moshe understands God, you
know, no it's not about me, it's about them, and before we
actually had that God said that essentially. You don't have a role
anymore now that I'm angry with them. Okay ויחל משה את פני
השם אלקיו v'yachal moshe et pnei hashem elokav Moshe sort of importuned
God. אמר רבי אלעזר amar rabbi elazar and now we're going to
explain this לשון lashon of ויחל, v'yachal, מלמד שעמד משה בתפילה לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא melamed she'amad moshe bitfillah lifnei hakadosh baruch hu Moshe
stood in prayer before God עד שהחלהו ad she'hechelohu until he החלהו
hechelohu which I thought it meant until he made him sick, like
חולה, choleh, right? רש"י Rashi says here
החלהו hechelohu means הפציר בו hiftsir bo until he sort of, you
know, sort of
overwhelmed him with the prayers. I don't know how they translate that
in the English. Importuned.
Importuned, I was going to say importuned, I couldn't think of the
word, until he importuned him. Anyway, but okay, so that's just translating
I think is שורש shoresh ויחל, v'yachal, but I did wonder if
it could mean until he made him sick. What do they have
there in the שטיינזלץ steinzaltz Charlie? Do they have do you see
החלהו? hechelohu? No.
Made him ill.
Ill. Oh, so they do have made him ill. Okay, like me,
not like רש"י. Okay.
There you go, alright. The רבא, Rava, I mean that's an image,
right? You do so much you make him ill. Okay. The רבא
אמר Rava amar עד שהפילו לנדרשא, ad shehipilo lenidrashah, שהפילו לנדרשא, shehipilo
lenidrashah, until he released God from His vow. Okay, this was what
Rava always quoted, release from the word of, we'll see, that's a
word of releasing from the vow. כתיב הכא ksiv hacha ויחל vayechal
and Moshe importuned, וכתיב התם vechsiv hasam לא יחל דברו. lo yachel
devaro. If a person takes a vow, they cannot allow the vow
to be violated, desecrated. אבל אמר מר, aval amar mar, הוא אינו
מיחל, hu eino mechal, a person cannot annul his vow, אבל אחרים
מחילין לו, aval acherim mechilin lo, others can be- can annul the
vow. So basically Moshe convened a בית דין Beis Din and annulled
God from His vow. What was God's vow? So God's vow was
that He basically said, you know, I'm going to destroy them, and
basically if God says something, that pretty much constitutes a vow. So,
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, where were we? Did I skip
a line? ושמואל אמר uShmuel amar מלמד שמסר עצמו למיתה עליהם. melamed
shemasar atzmo lemisah aleihem. He was prepared to die for them. שנאמר
ואם אין מחני נא מספרך. ve'im ayin mecheini na misifrecha. If and
if not, wipe me out from Your book, which would mean- which
would basically mean to, you know, let me- kill me, essentially is
the way he's reading. And what does that have to do with
ויחל? vayechal? So רש"י says it has to do with like a
חלל, chalal, like a corpse. אמר אברם אמר רבי יצחק amar Avram
amar Rabbi Yitzchak מלמד שהחילה עליהם מדת הרחמים. melamed shehechila aleihem midas
harachamim. He caused God's compassion to- to come to the people. ורבנן
אמרי verabanan amri to descend upon the people. מלמד שאמר משה לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא melamed she'amar Moshe lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu חולין הוא
לך מעשות כדבר הזה. chulin hu lecha me'asot kadavar hazeh. It would
be- it would be, you know, a desecration to You to do
such a thing. So the language of חולין, chulin, like חלילה, chalilah,
right, exactly. Okay. ויחל משה את פני ה', vayechal Moshe es penei
Hashem, Moshe importuned God. תניא tanya רבי אלעזר הגדול אומר Rabbi Elazar
Hagadol omer מלמד שעמד משה בתפילה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא עד שאחזו
אחילו. melamed she'amad Moshe bitfilah lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu ad she'achazo achilu.
Moshe stood before God until he was seized with אחילו. achilu. מאי
אחילו? mai achilu? Presumably Moshe was seized with אחילו. achilu. Until- what's
אחילו? achilu? אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar אשא דעצמות, esha de'atzmot,
a burning of the bones, like a- a fever. Now this- this
is a very interesting גמרא. מאי אשא דעצמות? mai esha de'atzmot? What
does a burning of the bones mean? אמר אביי amar Abaye אשתא
דגרמי, eshta degarmei, a burning of the bones.
Just translate it from the Hebrew to the Aramaic. But maybe somehow
that was an idiomatic expression which they understood, which meant a certain
type of a- of a fever like inside of your bones. זכור
לאברהם ליצחק ולישראל עבדיך. zechor le'Avraham le'Yitzchak ule'Yisrael avadecha. Remember Avraham, Yitzchak,
and Yisrael. אשר נשבעת להם בך, asher nishbata lahem bach, You swore
to them in Your name. מאי בך? mai bach? What does it
mean in Your name, by You? אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar
as normal you swear by God, so God swore by
God Himself, בך. bach. אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar אמר משה
לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא Moshe lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu רבונו של עולם,
Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the Universe. אלמלא נשבעת להם בשמים ובארץ,
imale nishbata lahem beshamayim uva'aretz, if You had sworn to them by
heaven and earth, הייתי אומר כשם ששמים וארץ בטלים כך שבועתך בטלה.
hayiti omer keshem sheshamayim va'aretz beteilim kach shevuatacha beteila. I would say
just as heaven and earth eventually will be destroyed, they're not- they're
not infinite, they're not forever, so Your oath can also be nullified.
ועכשיו שנשבעת להם בשמך הגדול, ve'achshav shenishbata lahem beshimcha hagadol, you swore
to them in Your own name. בי נשבעתי נאם ה', bi nishbati
ne'um Hashem, right? מה שמך הגדול
חי וקיים mah shimcha hagadol chai vekayam the same way Your name
is always- will last לעולם ולעולמי עולמים le'olam ule'olmei olamim for forever.
כך שבועתך קיימת לעולם ולעולמי עולמים. kach shevuatacha kayama le'olam ule'olmei olamim.
Your oath has to be forever, you can't back out. ותדבר אליהם
vatedaber aleihem and You spoke to them, ארבה את זרעכם arbe es
zar'acha I will cause your seed to increase, ככוכבי השמים וכל הארץ
הזאת אשר אמרתי kekochevei hashamayim vechol ha'aretz hazos asher amarti and- and
all this land that I have- that I have said I will,
you know, I will give to their seed, etc. ונחלו לעולם. venachalu
le'olam. האי אשר אמרתי, hai asher amarti, that I said. אשר אמרת
מי בעי ליה? asher amarta mi ba'ei lei? It should have said
You spoke to them and You said this land that You have
said. Because Moshe's speaking to God. אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar
עד כאן דברי תלמיד מכאן ואילך דברי הרב. ad kan divrei talmid
mikan ve'eilach divrei harav. Until now was Moshe speaking, You God spoke
to them, and then it was sort of God's, it was in
quote marks. You God spoke to them saying, quote, all this land
that I God have said, right? So it's in quote marks, so
the I, it's I, not You. מכאן ואילך
דברי הרב. mikan ve'eilach divrei harav. רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachmani amar אלו ואלו דברי תלמיד. elu ve'elu divrei talmid.
Moshe is saying both things. So what does it mean I said?
Moshe wasn't the one that said he'd give the land, God said.
אלא כך אמר משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, ela kach amar Moshe
lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu, this is what Moshe said to God. רבונו
של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the Universe. דברים שאמרת לי
לך אמור להם לישראל בשמי, devarim she'amarta li lech emor lahem leYisrael
bishmi, You told me to tell them in Your name that You
were going to give them the land. הלכתי ואמרתי להם בשמך, halachti
ve'amarti lahem bishmcha, I told them this in Your name. עכשיו מה
אני אומר להם? achshav mah ani omer lahem? What should I say
to them now? Meaning so it's like putting himself in the middle,
like, hey, You told me to tell them they're going to get
this land, now what am I supposed to tell them now? Right?
So אשר אמרתי, asher amarti, I said it to them. Okay, I
just want to finish to the end of the דף.
ויאמרו מבלתי יכולת ה', vaya'amru mibilti yacholet Hashem, that God, they'll say
God is not able. יכול ה' מיבעי ליה. yachol Hashem miba'ei lei.
It should have been able, not יכולת. yacholet. אמר רבי אלעזר amar
Rabbi Elazar משה Moshe לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא רבונו של עולם, Ribbono
Shel Olam, Master of the Universe. עכשיו יאמרו אומות העולם achshav yomeru
umot ha'olam תשש כחו כנקבה. tashash kocho kinekeivah. They'll say You have
become weak like a female, an image that the גמרא has a
couple of times in the use of the female. So it's יכולת
yacholet in the feminine. ואינו יכול להצילם, ve'eino yachol lehatzilam, and He
can't save them. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu
leMoshe ולא כבר ראו נסים וגבורות שעשיתי להם על הים? velo kvar
rau nissim u-gevurot she-asiti lahem al hayam? The nations won't say I
didn't have the ability, they saw what I did to them on
the ים סוף, Yam Suf, how all the miracles I did in
Egypt,
and משה Moshe said back, God, עדיין יש להם לומר, adayin yesh
lahem lomar, they could still say, מלך אחד יכול לעמוד, melech echad
yachol laamod, he could stand up against one king Pharaoh, ושלשים ואחד
מלכים אינו יכול לעמוד, u-shloshim ve-echad melachim eino yachol laamod, he can't
stand up against thirty-one kings that were in the land of כנען.
Kenaan. So they'll say, yeah, that was what you did then, but
you still weren't able, you wiped them out. אמר רבי יוחנן, מנין
שחזר הקדוש ברוך הוא והודה לו למשה, minayin she-chazar Hakadosh Baruch Hu
ve-hodah lo le-Moshe, how do we know God went back and he
sort of
admitted to משה Moshe, that משה Moshe, was
correct? שנאמר ויאמר ה׳ סלחתי כדברך, shene-emar vayomer Hashem salachti kidvarecha, I've
forgiven them according to your words, because of what you said that
the nations would say what they would say or maybe everything else
משה had said about אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov, that's why
I forgave them. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל כדברך עתידים אומות העולם לומר
כן, Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael kidvarecha atidim umot haolam lomar ken, the
nations would have said this if I'd wiped them out. אשרי תלמיד
שרבו מודה לו, ashrei talmid she-rabbo modeh lo, praise is the student
that his
master concedes to and admits him that he was right. ואולם חי
אני, ve-ulam chai ani, however, as I live,
you're not supposed to cut you off. You're not supposed, he wasn't
פוסקing, pasken he was just talking. Okay, ואולם חי אני, ve-ulam chai
ani, אמר רבא אמר רבי יצחק, amar Rava amar Rabbi Yitzchak, ומלמד
שאמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, u-melamed she-amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu
le-Moshe, משה, beautiful way of ending this, החייתני בדבריך, hecheyitani bidvarecha, חי
אני, chai ani, I have lived, you have given me life. ורש״י
ve-Rashi says it means given me life because now the nations won't
say I didn't have the ability, but there's also this beautiful idea
that if we make the proper prayers, so God is מודה בדבריך,
modeh bidvarecha, we in a sense give life to God because we,
as it were, enable God to do what God wants to do
in this world if we are able to pray in the proper
way. And just to finish this דרש, drash, רב סימאי לעולם יסדר
אדם שבחו של הקדוש ברוך הוא ואחר כך יתפלל, Rav Simai le-olam
yesader adam shivcho shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu ve-achar kach yitpalleil, now actually
getting into a הלכה halacha of prayer, one should first praise God
and then pray. Here the word יתפלל yitpalleil means בקשה, bakasha, before
they used the word תפילה tefillah to mean praising, here they're using
the word תפילה tefillah to mean the בקשה, bakasha, the request. What
is the central aspect of prayer? So first you start with the
praise, the first three ברכות, brachot, and then you move into the
בקשות bakashot in the middle. מנלן ממשה, menalan mi-Moshe, we know this
from משה, דכתיב ואתחנן אל ה׳, de-chtiv va-etchanan el Hashem,
now we're moving away from the עגל, Eigel,
I pray to God, I importuned God at the time, וכתיב, ve-chtiv,
how did he pray to God? ה׳ אלקים אתה החלות להראות את
עבדך את גדלך ואת ידך החזקה אשר מי א-ל בשמים ובארץ אשר
יעשה כמעשיך וכגבורותיך, Hashem Elokim atah hachilota leharot et avdecha et godlecha
ve-et yadcha hachazakah asher mi Eil bashamayim u-vaaretz asher yaaseh khe-maasecha u-khigvurotecha,
you have begun to show your greatness and your power, none is
like you in the heavens and the earth. So first praising God,
וכתיב בתריה אעברה נא ואראה את הארץ הטובה, ve-chtiv batreih ebrah na
ve-er-eh et haaretz hatovah, let me go in and see this beautiful
land. So first you praise God, that's the first three ברכות, brachot,
and then we move into the בקשות bakashot and we will continue
with this.